Cool. Okay. So, we've started recording.
Uh I wanted to get started now. Uh
thanks everyone for for joining. Uh
September 18th. Uh today we're we're
still looking at the first half of the
active inference textbook from 2022. Uh
today is for chapter 4, but we can take
the conversation wherever we like or if
anyone has anything they're interested
in in particular. Um, but I did want to
touch a little bit on chapter 4 just for
the sake of the the scheduling and kind
of connecting it with with previous
chapters which is that um
chapter one we had like a very loose
general introduction act of inference as
a uh first and foremost is it is a
framework. It's highly um related to and
entails the uh free energy principle,
the idea that uh everything the brain
does must
minimize free energy. Um we're we're
introduced in chapter two to the low
road to active inference. So we're
talking about kind of basian frameworks
using kind of basian statistics or
mechanics. Um it is still you know a
topic for debate. um for those who
adhere to something like a basian brain
hypothesis whether they think that it is
expressly a basian sort of framework
that the brain itself follows or if it
does something like that. Um there are
kind of representationalist versus
non-representationalist accounts of what
the brain does. Um the the the core
aspect here is that something like
basian statistics and mechanics are
involved. Uh most put most generally is
the idea that whenever we come to a
situation, we have priors prior sort of
evidence um that we bring to a situation
when confronting new observations when
eliciting new acts um actions when
updating our beliefs along the way. And
uh so then chapter 3 is the from sort of
the the mountain top of the high road
looking down which is the claim that um
it essentially begins with the the free
energy principle and talking about why
is it that organisms that that entities
things people um brains or otherwise how
do they continue to exist uh and persist
um how do they stay alive when they are
living? Um and and it's it's there that
the free energy principle comes in as
that is how they do that and why they do
that. Why they continue to persist is
through this this kind of repeated
continuous engagement with free energy
minimization
um in order to sustain oneself in order
for all necessary parts to sort of
self-organize the the sort of guiding
principle is is free energy minimization
based upon you know several decades of
work that that Carl Fristen and others
to Par and Zulo and and um Isaura and
and others have have have kind of
empirically established in various ways
uh through neuroiming neuroscience kind
of related studies um working with cells
and cell cultures up to neuroiming data
in the human brain or the pavalian brain
and um and then it's here in chapter 4
that things kind of come back around and
we start getting a bit more into the the
the sort of like here's how we put
things together these basian frameworks
Free energy. What is free energy? How
does that how does that work and how
does it function? Active inference for
better or worse is slightly notorious
for having relatively complex um kind of
equations and formalisms involved. So
it's it's really in chapter 4 that that
we were exposed more deeply to to a lot
of the aspects of that. Um already uh in
the in the first section we return to
Baz's rule where we know that we have a
prior or a prior belief about hidden
states. We have our our marginal
likelihood or our evidence which is that
probability of y which is kind of like
the probability of observations.
Um and then uh the conditional
probabilities of each on each which
would be the posterior which is the
probability of X conditioned on Y. It's
kind of what what do we believe given
the observations we we have received
right conditioned on these observations
this evidence this this this model
evidence this data um and then the the
the flip of that which is the likelihood
which is what is the probability of this
observation conditioned on what I
believe to be the case what I believe
the hidden states of the world currently
are right and it's with those four
components and using bases role to kind
of move and compute between them. Um
that that we kind of proceed and then
from there the issue has to do with
computational tractability.
Um, you can imagine for someone I I I
attempt to use kind of everyday examples
of these things, but for for someone who
decides that they want to go to a
particular location, say they want to go
to a store, um, they want to buy
groceries, they'll they'll get they'll
they'll purchase food, they'll gain
their sustenance, you know, for the day
or for the week or the next few weeks or
otherwise, um, you know, they'll come
home and they'll maintain their
homeostasis. Um if if this person is say
I don't know in Par lives in Paris and
they're the store is a few blocks away
in Paris then the idea that they need to
run some kind of broadscale
inference over all known locations that
they're aware of on the planet whether
that be in the United States or in you
know um China Russia or otherwise
um that that it's we intuitively we
would think why would you need to think
of all these other places. Similarly
here in a certain sense it's like well
if you had to kind of integrate or sum
over that level of vastness in a in a
computationally speaking in that vast of
a state space um things would become
quickly intractable uh inefficient very
very energy and timeconsuming
um we we already know that there'd be a
lot of unnecessary computation involved
but that that's not the point right it's
it's like this is based upon how the the
brain works, whether it has that
additional perspective on is it
efficient for me to think about what's
going on in um in the United States in
this case, right? Um so, so to speak a
little bit more technically, the idea is
that we use something called variational
basian inference here. Um where the the
authors claim that they they kind of
exploit what's known as Jensen's
inequality.
It's this idea that uh and it's not just
an idea and there's kind of an
illustrated proof of this but that the
idea that a log of an expectation is
always greater than or equal to the
expectation of a log. It's there that
they kind of do this um this trick
without meaning to to to um make it
sound like an informal thing. It's very
reasonable thing to do in variational
methods. um but to actually like have
this kind of variational posterior that
allows for variety of other
computations. So they talk about like
mean field approximation and making
different kinds of assumptions of how
things work as sort of these shortcuts
um that allow one to or allow a brain or
allow some kind of um process to to
navigate this otherwise intractable
state space that it's confronted with.
perhaps composed of. Um, all this is to
say that this one is much more
biologically plausible. It allows for
focusing more on what is more
significant in the moment. Allows for
marginalizing out from massive state
spaces like we only need to focus on
Paris because that is where the store
is. That's sort of that sort of logic.
Another term that they they use here is
importance sampling. Right? So being
able to to kind of hone in on the the
what what's more salient um in the
moment actually having the kind of
mathematical
architecture that allows for you know
someone who wants to do active inference
or other forms of uh research and
computational modeling like that gives
us a means to ourselves like write this
down uh write down the formalisms or the
equations right um and being able to to
make things more ractive. So um so on
page 66 we have an equation a more
express equation for v for variational
free energy which is uh divergence minus
log model evidence we know from the
>> Andrew do you want to share your screen?
>> Uh oh yeah am I am I not sharing my
screen?
>> Uh the symposium page
>> it's still the symposium. Yeah.
Flip that over here.
X64.4.
Here we are.
Yeah. So this is this is uh one way of
formalizing variational free energy. Um
it depends on what everyone wants to
discuss today. Sometimes I go a little
too far into these these like uh chapter
summaries. Um so I'll just more quickly
say like we can we can
we can remember many of these pieces
from previous chapters, right? We know
that X is uh representative of hidden
states, hidden states of the world. Y
are our sensory evidence or observations
that we receive. So whenever we see this
probability of X conditioned on Y, we
already remember like oh these are
posteriors. We see probability of Y that
is the evidence. This Q of X is the
interesting piece that comes in through
Jensen's inequality and getting to the
variational methods. rather than a P,
you have a Q. Recall Daniel saying,
"Mind your P's and Q's in the past to to
kind of remember that." Um, but Q is
that variational
um Q is that variational posterior,
right? It's just to represent like now
now we're in the realm of using
variational methods or that it's it's
this Q that we use to denote that um out
of sort of remembrance and um and then
from there we get into like here are a
variety of different sorts of models
that
where we could where we could apply um
these kinds of methods. Some of them may
not actually call for variational
methods. Um, it depends on the
complexity of the problem at hand. But
as far as free energy minimization goes,
you would be using variational methods
regardless of the circumstance. Um, so
these models for example, um, for anyone
unfamiliar with doing any kind of
modeling in general, a really good
example is just this one in the top left
where we do have a prior, we do have a
likelihood which is the probability of
the observation conditioned on uh, in
the states of the world. And um, a
really good example would be uh, a COVID
test, right? Um we like we some would
like to believe that a COVID test could
one to one tell you if if you have COVID
or not, right? But at the end of the
day, ultimately there is an accuracy
rate because what's really going on with
a co COVID test is a kind of modeling
paradigm that uh can go by the name of
binary classification trying to decide
do you have COVID, do you not have
COVID, right? And so what's going on
here to use this as modeling a this is
could be a model of a COVID test is the
probability of X is kind of like saying
what is the probability of having COVID?
We don't really know. The test is sort
of like your your sensory receptor here,
right? it's going to take in some kind
of bodily, you know, fluid uh in in some
shape or form and then it's going to um
run some kind of internal complication
as it were uh based on how the the test
is designed and give you final reading
at the end. So it's it's there that you
know based upon
whatever is going on in the the the the
material that's given to that test
there's an inference being made about
whether you have COVID or not and that's
being returned to you sort of a separate
agent to receive that as your own
observation. Um, so that's it. It it
leads into this division where you have
things like true positives and and true
negatives and false positives and false
negatives that the test told you that
you have COVID when in fact you don't
and so now you have a false positive.
Um, all of those kinds of dynamics are
readily captured within this like given
given what the test finds within the the
bodily fluid given to it. But is uh what
is the probability of seeing
the that composition of that bodily
fluid given you have COVID versus given
you don't have COVID, right? Like there
it's as if there's a kind of inference
being made. We could do the same thing.
We could say, "Oh, uh what is the
probability of me seeing that this test
tells me I have COVID conditioned on me
having COVID? If I trust this test, it's
probably very high. If I don't trust
this test very well, then well, I don't
know why I'm using it in the first
place, but more important like to the
the point here, it'd probably be a much
lower probability, right? Um, so that
that that's kind of the that's kind of a
shorthand of uh, you know, how to how to
examine these models and from there it
gets simpler as long as you kind of
catch on to the first one. This is
called factor graph fory factor graph
notation. So, um,
like this upper right one, it's like,
well, now we have two different
variables that are going into Y. You
know, what what is what is my weight? It
could be a function of my my height and
my diet, right? And those are the two
thing those are the X and the Z that
that end up leading to a Y, right?
Um or
you could have a single variable that's
impacting two other variables, right? So
how well do I sleep at night and how
well do I function during the day are
both functions of you know how stressed
out I am.
So and then you can have these longer
kind of running chains right of one
thing that impacts another thing that in
turn impacts a third and that that can
start to expand outward further.
So
and then
these models here
are in many ways similar to the previous
ones although granted they're more
complex. These are only two models and
there many more circles and squares to
look at. Um but the main idea is that
we're moving in the direction of what
we'll see in chapter seven and 8 which
is kind of these more fullyfledged
predictive coding and active inference
models. Um both of these are formally
equivalent. They just use different
symbols. Uh so in the top one you have
like pi, you have o, you have s. the
bottom you have V, you have Y, and you
have X. Um, the only reason why they do
that is that this top one is for what's
called discrete time models. You can
think of discrete in the sense of
colors, not as like a RGB like color
scale, but just red versus blue versus
green, like these discreet specific
things or am I hungry? Yes or no. Right?
as opposed to the bottom model which
would be used for continuous time which
is where you start to look more at
scales. You look more at things like
continuous continu continuously valued
metrics. So heart rate um
um signals from an EEG electrode, you
know, sensor in neuroiming studies. um
the amount of money in your wallet
potentially if you bring it down to the
cents. Um which could also be due to
discrete sense of how many pennies do
you have but uh so the main thing is
that we have discrete time and
continuous time. There's some nice
literature elsewhere that shows that
they kind of they both at at their root
exhibit the same kind of behavior
virtually. So they both reduce back down
to the free energy principle in a sense.
Um which is really nice. It keeps the
framework very consistent. Um and yet
you can use either one depending on the
situation again if you're trying to
model something. We only focus on the
top one. And I'm already going into this
more than I need to because it'll all
come back in chapters seven and eight.
Um but this is kind of where we start
getting to the idea of oh from left to
right there's a temporal
horizon that is these are the these are
about beliefs about h how hidden states
change over time
um and then reading it top to down we
can see how an o observation is taken in
s a hidden state is inferred
and then inferring a hidden state of the
world leads to pi and action or policy
to be taken and that all of these things
are more or less kind of kind of
synchronized with one one another and
they proceed processually. So, so you
know you take in an observation about
the world, you update your beliefs about
what is going on in the world given that
observation and finally you move on to
action or planning or or carrying out
some kind of action in response to not
directly to the observation but to your
intermediary belief about the world that
was updated.
So my stomach growls. I infer that I'm
hungry. I decide or act to go get food
to save my hunger or information gain. I
I start looking at restaurants where to
get some food or something. Check the
fridge. Do I have any food? Then
so
there there are plenty of other topics
going on in here, but I already know
that that someone wanted to to to
discuss um potentially other parts of
the book or other parts of this chapter.
Um so I'll just wrap up that there will
be more of these kinds of things in
chapter five that's much more focused on
what's called message passing um and
kind of the neurobiological aspects. We
get discussion of sort of um deep versus
superficial pyramidal cells um in in in
cortical microircuitry in the brain. Um
and and so a lot of these things just
have to do with passing prediction error
uh and and updating beliefs accordingly
kind of at this this sort of more micro
level as it were. But that's it's there
that we can start to look at how these
things actually map to biological
coralates and are not just sort of free
floating mathematical ideas without any
empirical grounding.
Generalized coordinates of motion. these
play out in the continuous time models
that I mentioned earlier. Um that these
are especially
they're they're very important for
understanding continuous time models. Um
but also they're very illustrative
whenever it comes to the idea of you
know reflex arcs and and motor
movements. So, you know, how is it that
that through a discrete decision in my
brain to, you know, grab uh my cup of
coffee near me that my arm actually like
is able to navigate itself to my cup of
coffee, right? Um the trajectory, the
kind of physics involved in that so on.
Of course, that that kind of computation
can play out through variety of other um
examples, not just movement, but I think
movement is a quick one of kind of
getting at it. Here again, we have more
of these. It's really just showing
conceiving of this as a kind of message
passing, right? a message passing
between different neuronal populations
in the brain or collections of neurons
or potentially different brain regions
depending on what level of ex
abstraction you want to move to uh
whenever you do you're doing this kind
of modeling or trying to understand um a
process.
So I'll wrap up there. Um
yeah. Um
I think a team were you interested in
um you mentioned something about another
chapter or if there was anything you're
considering.
>> Yeah, I had a a question about uh about
I think this this comes back in chapter
4 about the pragmatic and epistemic
value or I don't know about the
exploitation exploration trade-off. I
was kind of curious as to how this is uh
how the how an organism or an agent uh
trades off these two these two modes of
uh of of reducing uh of reducing
uncertainty of surprisal
because it's I mean as I understand it
in the short term you want to reduce the
the pragmatic value the pragmatic uh
prag I forget how it's called in the in
the book yeah the pragmatic value. But
in the long term, you want to reduce the
epistemic value because uh in if you if
you make if you if you're in an
environment that uh that is unknown, you
have to explore and then this
exploration will will give you the the
ability to to be less surprised in the
future. So you you kind of trade off the
the the short-term surprise for the
long-term one. So I'm kind of curious as
to how practically this is done like uh
uh what kind of uh what kind of uh of uh
situations like uh the what kind of
scenarios is an organism placed in like
the ones that I sketched out is are
there other ones that that you can think
of like uh where the where the pragmatic
value is is better than the epistemic
value or vice versa or is it I don't
know is or did I cover everything maybe
in my in my kind of explaining explain
the question but
I don't know if it's clear
>> everything that you said makes a lot of
sense and it's a it's a very significant
question here um it is for active
inference and and they do kind of make a
point about this whenever I've know
given um done presentations where I'm
describing active inference to others
this is actually a point that I I
particularly am fond of and it's part of
why I uh am interested in active
inference as opposed to other
frameworks. Um there there are many
reasons why I personally like it more
than other frameworks. Um but but this
is one of those reasons. Uh so here on
the the screen I've come to this is
equation 2.6 which I would infer is
probably in chapter 2. I can't remember
off the top of my head, but they usually
follow that numbering. Um, and we'll
just I this is quite a monster of an
equation because it is technically a
singular full equation. Um, but you can
just read this top line with information
gain and pragmatic value. Um, which is
those those terms that you were
referring to. Um and they do for better
or worse there are a lot of different
words that are used. So sometimes
information gain is called epistemic
value just to have another value that
can be kind of more readily like coupled
to the idea of pragmatic value. Um
information gain works as well. Um and
and then at the second line you see this
is just an equals sign. So these are
actually one way of doing expected free
energy which is G. You'll notice that
that's different from F. Um but and that
that's an important distinction. But
fortunately that's the only distinction
we need to make. The only two forms of
var of of free energy that we're looking
at in any of these models are
variational free energy and expected
free energy. What is expected free
energy? It's incredibly similar to
variational free energy. It's still a
variational basian uh inference method.
Um many of the formalisms are the same.
You're still working with a prior and a
likelihood and all the rest. The only
difference is that variational free
energy is sort of like a reactivity to
the moment. An expected free energy is
what's related in what we would call
planning. uh you know having a kind of
policy horizon where you you know if if
I infer right now that I'm you know I
receive an observation my stomach is
growling I'm surprised by that I didn't
think I was hungry but now I'm starting
to think I must be there's some kind of
surprisal that happens um you know my my
variational free energy of that moment
so to speak would probably uh go up so
remember the idea is we want to minimize
that as uh and that's what chapter 4 in
part is about is that variational free
energy is a an upper bound on surprisal.
So by minimizing variational free
energy, you're necessarily going to be
um approximately minimizing surprisal.
So so back to that kind of funny example
I'm giving. Um you know there's
surprisal in the moment. Oh no, I'm
hungry. Now I start planning. What do I
do? Right? How do I we we would call
this in technical terms like policy
inference. I need I I I infer a state of
the world is that I'm hungry. Now I need
to infer what policy to take. That's why
we have these two different equations,
right? But they're they're they're
essentially both variational methods.
It's just expected free energy is
involved in planning. And it's kind of
it I I I can't remember if it's Fristen
or or someone else, but someone has
phrased this as sort of the free energy
of the future. um like what what free
energy do you expect uh given you do
this action which could lead to this
change in the world what kind of v what
level of free energy do you expect from
that right and so these kinds of
computations could could basically be
carried out into the future up to some
horizon
um you know if are you thinking about
your life in the long term and where
you'll be in 10 years from now are you
thinking more about going to get
food uh or or are you thinking about
making plans with a friend next week
where there's a lot of things that could
happen between now and next week. Um in
any case, you're you're you're thinking
into the future and it's there that we
sort of depart from simply
complexity minus accuracy, a variational
free energy of the moment and instead we
start thinking going forward. And so now
to get a little bit more deeply into
kind of the way you you phrase the
question of looking at information gain
again otherwise known as empymic value
and pragmatic value. One way of viewing
these in kind of simple terms is
information gain means actions that will
help you learn more uh about your
environment. Uh really more
specifically, it's saying you want to
maximize the difference between your
beliefs about the world given
observations
and actions
versus your beliefs about the world
given
actions. Like regardless of whatever it
is you're saying. So, and to this day,
it's still been hard for me to come up
with a fully intuitive example of what
that means. But, but the main thing
you'll notice between these two cues,
uh, is the why. The why is present here.
It's kind of like saying, well, well, I
think that if I do this, then this will
be what comes out of that. The the
hidden states of the world will change
in this way. Oh, if I if I eat this
food, I will no longer be hungry. Um,
that would be the right term, right? I I
I I did something and I'm trying to
change a hidden state about my hunger,
which I can only infer. Um, the the
earlier term is kind of like saying,
"Oh, well, I I ate this thing. It turns
out it had no caloric value uh and was
very small and hardly fills my stomach,
so it turns out I'm still hungry." like
I don't know if eating this particular
food will actually sate me or not,
right? Um probably a better example
would be the idea of reading a book to
find more information, right? Like well,
you've never observed that book before,
so there's no why in it. um you don't
really know what you'll have gained from
that but maybe by reading it you'll have
more information about the world around
you thanks to actually observing the
outcome of doing this particular action
right another way of viewing it is just
if I do something if I don't know what
will happen then I don't know if this
action is ever going to be useful for
for anything right um or maybe the
action just may or may not be useful for
a particular context
um whatever it is, we're going to do it
just for the sake of seeing what comes
out of it. Right? You think of a child,
children do this all the time. They're
incredibly uh curious and sometimes they
do things whether they should do them or
not do them or otherwise um you know
just just to see what occurs. And then
pragmatic value is quite different. Here
we see a a term that we haven't seen yet
um but it comes up all over the place in
chapter 7 whenever it gets back into the
modeling C. And this is this C is is is
very important. This is used to denote
preferences. Um, there are other words
that this goes by, but and and
preferences is kind of a loose term that
that I think it's kind of a carryover
from some economics literature or
thinking about rational actors or or or
probability theory, what it means to
have like um a subjective sense of
probability or beliefs. Um, preferences
here could mean one's preference for a
certain, you know, chocolate or vanilla
ice cream or something, but it could
also relate to homeostasis, right? So I
I prefer to have my and none of this
none of the computations I'm talking
about here none of this is assumed to
necessarily be a conscious process but
like in a sense my my brain prefers that
that my my blood oxygenation in my in my
body be at a certain level or my heart
rate be around a certain level right
that is what keeps me living or
surviving. So preferences in that sense
can also be you know depending on how
you view that like to some degree could
be genetically derived just as much as
you know they be learned through
experience over time of like oh I
actually I tried that chocolate ice
cream and I did decide I like it more
and I prefer that as a more conscious
thing right so it's it's kind of like at
various scales but the the main point is
that you see that like pragmatic atic
value for anyone who's interested or or
engages in things like reinforcement
learning um and and kind of machine
learning models. Um th this would be
kind of like a reward function, right?
Like I there are certain things that I
need to do in order to stay alive or oh
there are certain things that I prefer.
Um I should go after those. um if I do
this particular action is that will I it
will I get what I want out of it or what
I prefer out of it. Right? So that I
mean the the autonomic nervous system
does this. It repeatedly tries to
regulate the body in different ways
depending upon the circumstance at hand
and it tends to be attracted towards
bringing you back to a nice preferred so
to speak regulated state. Um so
pragmatic I I I I give all this detail
because pragmatic value is is it is like
a reward function. It's kind of like an
attractor an attracting system that the
book gets into that kind of idea more in
chapter 8. Um so then finally to bring
it together. So, okay, well, information
gain and pragmatic value. How do we
pick? How do we pick if we should, you
know, should should I go straight for
some food or should I like look at other
kinds of food I've never had before? Or
in chapter 7, we have a T-aze example
where there's a there's a mouse who can
get a reward by going either to one side
of the maze or the other, to the left
arm or to the right. and it doesn't know
which side the cheese is on. Um, it has
an option to get an informative cue from
its environment. Uh, that will tell it
where the cheese is, if it's on the left
or right side. Um,
the the mouse very well could just
guess, go for the left arm or the right
arm, or if it gets that cue, which isn't
immediately giving it any reward, so to
speak. it's not getting the cheese, but
it is giving it more information about
the environment around it. Maybe it
should do that. So, a lot of people use
that this T-mase example uh as a kind of
kind of like how how do people you know
how do how does any agent or any entity
or organism make these kinds of
decisions or or or balance these kinds
of trade-offs.
Um with active inference there all
potential actions are already scored
against each other based on how much
information each one of them will give
you and the pragmatic value that it will
give you. So at the end of the day here
we don't have to choose this whole
equation tells you everything in one go.
You compute information gain for this
action. You compute pragmatic value in
this action. at the end you get your
amount of expected free energy that gets
compared to all other actions. So
there's a phrase in this textbook they
say that that sort of like exploration
or information gain and exploitation or
pragmatic value or reward seeking uh
naturally balance out. They don't
balance out with sense of like okay now
they're half and half like that. That's
not what that means. it just means that
they're both included in the equation as
it were. They both function there. Um uh
an alternative way of saying this is um
and this is why like this is part of
what brought me to active inference on
this point. Um, in in reinforcement
learning, uh, people will try and decide
on the exploration exploitation dilemma
by saying, "Oh, well, we'll just have
our agent always go for the reward, but
we'll include uh an extra rule. We're
going to hardcode some rule in there
that tells the agent to instead explore,
which means do something random 10% of
the time." And that mean that that
that'll make sure that the agent learns
a little bit more and doesn't just
repetitively do the same thing over and
over and doesn't get stuck in some kind
of suboptimal, you know, solution. Um,
that is that is a very kind of like that
is the computer programmer's kind of
decision to to do that, right? to
hardcode this rule that tells you to do
something random 10% of the time. Or
they can make it as complex as they
like, but at the end of the day, they're
kind of they're kind of hard coding
something in there that just is forced
randomness to make sure that you don't
always do the thing that you're
otherwise hooked up to do. Um, this is
kind of like saying, oh no, you you are
also hooked up to do things to get info.
you are kind of hooked up to explore it
and it's not purely random like these
are all components of the model that
already exist because this is a basian
framework which means to say what is
going to give you the most information
is going to be based upon your prior
beliefs right so if you want to read a
book to gain more information um say
you're a researcher in a particular you
know established field of science
science or something. It's very unlikely
that you're going to like read some
random fully random book from the
library. It's more likely that you'll
end up looking for books that relate to
your field of interest or maybe you're
working on some kind of, you know,
project or paper or dissertation or
otherwise. And so you find a a book that
seems to most match, you know, kind of
the direction that you're going for so
that you can gain information. So, so
it's more like those kinds of dynamics
are what are involved uh in exploration
under the active inference framework.
Um, intuitively to me they make a lot
more sense. Not saying that we should
always rely upon intuition and
understanding these things, but but it
was here that I was like, "Oh, like that
that actually makes a lot more sense if
you were to formalize the idea of
exploration, not as pure randomness, but
rather you're coming to the situation
with what you already know uh so far or
believe so far about the hidden states
of the world and actions and what you've
seen in the past, what might happen in
the future.
Um,
so that's kind of what is meant through
a natural balancing of of exploration,
exploitation. I kind of turned that into
a lecture though, so I want to apologize
for that. Did that kind of get at kind
of what you were asking team or do you
have any follow-ups on that you're
curious about?
>> Was it was pretty clear and exhaustive,
but yeah, if I think of something, I
I'll just I'll ask you later, but for
now, it's quite good.
I mean I mean I it's kind of I mean I'm
just processing it right now that you
said that it's kind of baked into the
model and I'm trying to understand how
how this is uh like because it's such a
big thing where in reinforcement
learning they talk about the
exploitation exploration trade-off and
I'm trying to see how how what you said
right now is that it's basically it
basically solves the trade-off is what I
understand.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's like what the way to
like whatever exploration an agent gets
into um
it'll be based on its preceding beliefs,
right? It'll it'll it'll and at the end
of the day it'll be whatever it is
whatever it does to get more information
will be all tied back to minimizing free
energy. Right? That's sort of the the
broad simp like despite all the very
complex looking equations which the rest
of these are just different ways of
breaking down expected free energy.
Right? So these are just other ways of
doing that that all
equate to one another or kind of like
upper bounds of one another. Um, this is
the one I usually come back to and most
people come back to is information
gained, pragmatic value or it's
exploration, exploitation. But yeah, so
there's no there's no like
do something random here. Um, unless
unless the agent had a belief about what
it means to do something random, I guess
that would technically be a component in
the model. Um, but it it would depend on
the the agents beliefs at the time. If
it thinks it should genuinely do
something random, my bet is it probably
won't. Um, most of the time it'll do
something that gives more context to
other things that the agent does care
about, right? Um, and both of these are
involved. So again, it's like I'm doing
a project on psychiatry. I will probably
go go to the psychiatry section of the
library to read books that directly
relate to the pragmatic value to be
attained from like continuing my
research. Right? So that their info gain
and reward or pragmatic value are both
involved, right? So that's you know it's
not not so much a tradeoff as it is a
kind of um
summation of these values. Um yeah. Uh,
Tara, you have your hand up.
>> Yeah. No, I um uh thanks for all of this
background and and I feel like you're
getting towards some of the questions
that I've been thinking about. Um, one
of the things is just um, uh, I was
listening to one of the lectures and
someone made a statement about um, how
deep is your generative model and um, I
loved that that quote and so I've been
would love to to hear more about how how
our beliefs are encoded in some of these
equations. I I think I just heard you
say that um you know and that that the
preferences
um are sort of in that C for the
pragmatic value and then um and then you
gestured towards the the why as as the
place where we might encode some of
these um uh beliefs. But um you know
trying to and and also thinking about
how beliefs get encoded um in terms of
time scale you know like are we are we
encoding the beliefs of the experiences
I've had over the past week or am I
encoding the experiences that I have
over the course of generations you know
so like this um and and and and then the
question of to what extent they're in
hidden states um you know, I'm I'm sort
of aware of my thinking, or at least I'd
like to believe my thinking over the
past week, but I may not be as aware of
some of the things I've inherited over
the course of, you know, generations.
Um, and that that I'm I'm interacting
with both of those sets of beliefs.
Anyway,
>> sure.
>> Yeah. No, good good uh thanks for that
and good question. It's um there there
are a few different things I could say.
uh with so with the idea of encoding
beliefs or at least how we will
typically represent them whenever we you
know try our hand at act like you know
making a model ourself and putting it
into sort of a computational program to
to to sort of model you know an organism
a mouse in the teams or whatever. Um
most frequently we we're working with um
at least it it kind of the case
everywhere but we we'll go with the
discrete time models like as I mentioned
earlier um those are usually done in I'm
trying to see if we um I'm trying to
remember if this is a figure and
equation we're usually working with
matrices
um
might be this is chapter
Okay. So, they'll look something like
this. And this is back to the the
teammates's example.
Um,
so this this is a little out out of
context, but this this these matrices
are all part of um what an overall
established B matrix, which is kind of
the common nomenclature for better or
worse. Active inference kind of does
this thing where we start from A and
then we go to B and then we go to C and
there's no inherent meaning for why it's
a B. Um it's used to denote what's
called a state transitions matrix. And
so this would effectively be an agent's
beliefs about how hidden states change
over time conditioned on what they do
like conditioned on policies. Honestly,
out of all of the different components,
it's it's the most it's the most complex
one. Uh because it involves both time
and it also involves action. Um so, uh
I'm currently hungry. I believe with a
probability of one that if I eat
something, I will no longer be hungry.
Right? So, that's it's like a a hidden
state of the world right now, an action
I can do right now, which is to eat. in
the next proverbial time step uh I will
no longer be hungry like that by by me
doing that I have changed the state of
the world and that so th this this is
directly you know a part of action
whenever we're talking about action and
perception in active inferex and
elsewhere um so this is kind of how they
would they would look right um is that
the these rows and columns are like
saying like oh if the agent well I'd
have to break this down further but But
each one of these has to do with an
action and has to do with the agent
moving uh through through the T-maze. So
it believes with the probability of one
that if it starts at the the center and
it chooses to not move then it will
remain at the center or it uh
alternatively if it starts at the center
it could believe with a probability of
one that if it goes left then it will
end up being uh at at the left arm of
the the maze. Right? So the the um these
are the ways of kind of attempting to
simpl simplify that kind of logic and in
like verbally. Um but all of this is to
say that these are just effectively a
lot of matrices with their own
respective kind of probability values.
Um and then whenever it comes to real
time inference all of these are playing
into decision making. uh free energy is
kind of just um in one sense a kind of
computation over a bunch of matrices uh
trying to find what combination is
needed to achieve the lowest value of of
of free energy. Um that's that's what it
all comes back down to. Um, and you can
imagine if we used all of these
matrices, every single bit of them
fully, and tried to fully compute
surprisal, um, that it would be a lot.
And so it would be too much and it would
be very far away from something like
like biological plausibility. Like the
human brain runs effectively on the
calories equivalent to I think two
bananas um, every day. Um it it would be
incredible if if we did a massive full
computation over everything with with
billions of neurons at any given given
moment and only need to eat so much food
to survive. So um I hope that that was
kind of kind of gave some perspective on
those things about this encoding and
then with actually yeah with um with
with temporal horizon which is another
good question. Um, so not only can you
have kind of these state transitions
like I was referring to, um, as in like,
oh, if I go left, I will then be in the
left square. If I go right, I will, uh,
I'll be in the right part of the maze,
excuse me. Um but you could also have
these kinds of active infer not just
active inference but the brain generally
this is this is very broad throughout
the literature whether you're kind of
doing a more fristenoriented
um um you know perspective on these
things or not is that the brain tends to
work kind of hierarchically there are
interacting systems between one another
right and they can all kind of operate
at their own respective time scales So,
um
I I'm someone who who's done some work
and and we'll be presenting of it some
of it next month uh on um u
post-traumatic stress disorder. And
we're trying to computationally model
some dynamics that are involved in that.
Not not the experience of a traumatic
event, but rather what comes after that,
someone's capacity for kind of like
navigating the world around them. So, a
lot of that has had to do with looking
at the differences between whenever
someone with PTSD or anyone regardless
of whether you've been diagnosed with
that or not. Um, whenever you come into
contact with with a phenomena, you have
a certain part of your brain, a region
of your brain, including what's called
the amygdala, which is very responsible
for helping with threat detection. Um,
other things too, reward detection. In
fact, it it works at a very fast pace.
Uh whenever whenever you're you're
engaging with the environment around
you, it actually it it tends to activate
and then send information up, you could
say perhaps hierarchically to the
prefrontal cortex, which is the area
that we most commonly associate with,
you know, consciousness, rationality,
deliberate decision making, not
impulsivity.
Um, so it works at a slower pace than
the amygdala does, right? Um, an even
slower functioning part of the brain,
the hippocampus, is where so much of
your long-term memory is stored,
including things from that happened
whenever you were 5 years old.
um the way that these different areas or
regions of the brain kind of interact
with one another and we can think about
it as a form of you know that's what
that's what all these kind of wildl
looking formalisms are for as a bunch of
kind of um message passing schemes
between these parts of the brain
themselves operating at different
scales. That's what allows for a lot of
these more intricate kind of uh deep uh
both temporally deep and then just kind
of computationally deep uh you know
broader systems that make up you know
what is one's brain if not many many
smaller parts. They're all interacting
with one another um in different ways
and sending different kinds of signals
to one another. So, um, someone could
reflect about what's happened to them
over this past week, which will both
bring up memories of today and things
that are currently in short-term memory.
It will also start to retrieve from that
hippocample structure I mentioned a
moment ago. um um kind of longer term
memory of what happened you know say
last uh Thursday or whatever it was and
start to kind of construct through
observing one's thoughts as it were
hidden states of the world including for
this moment like what does it mean to
reflect on this past week what was going
on this past week what do I make of that
is there some kind of meaning could to
to to consolidate and condense out of
that um you It's we it's ultimately a
kind of belief uh structured there. So
I I also recognize we kind of ran up on
on time here. Uh so we will have to have
to end. But uh I uh team and Carrie, I
really appreciate your folks questions.
Um appreciate the engagement. uh next
week at this time um this exact time
next week we'll be talking about the
Daniel and I do this kind of dovetailing
back and forth between cohorts and
chapters. So it'll it'll be me here at
this time next week, but we'll be uh
talking about I believe chapter 8 um in
the textbook which is on continuous time
models. um that will have to do with
some interesting things that have to do
with attractors. It'll have to do with
some things that relate to this kind of
message passing stuff. But it'll be
it'll be really focused on some other
ideas too of like there's a concept
called generalized synchrony which is
what happens whenever you could use it
to model like communication for example.
What does it mean for two agents to
interact with one another? And what does
it mean whenever we start to realize
that like it's more commonly than not
their beliefs are more likely to kind of
synchronize over time as they continue
to communicate. Um, which is found in
humans. Even this the speed at which we
speak tends to modulate to one another
whenever we're in conversation with one
another or we start to borrow idioms and
things. But that's an empirical example.
But anyway, so it's it's a different
kind of chapter was rather rather
interesting. Um and uh yeah, so hope to
to see me next week. Drop in to that
one. Drop into the morning one. Um any
questions regardless of what chapter it
is, uh Daniel and I will be happy to to
discuss them. So um all right. Thanks so
much everyone.
Take care.
>> Thanks. Take care.
Thanks.